<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "jBPM_Reference_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="pluggable">
  <title>Pluggable architecture</title>
  
  <para>The functionality of jBPM is split into modules.  Each module 
  has a definition and an execution (or runtime) part.  The central 
  module is the graph module, made up of the 
  <literal>ProcessDefinition</literal> and the <literal>ProcessInstance</literal>.
  The process definition contains a graph and the process instance represents 
  one execution of the graph.  All other functionalities of jBPM are grouped into 
  optional modules.  Optional modules can extend the graph module with extra 
  features like context (process variables), task management, timers, ...</para>

  <figure id="pluggable.architecture.image">
    <title>The pluggable architecture</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/pluggable.architecture.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The pluggable architecture in jBPM is also a unique mechanism to 
  add custom capabilities to the jBPM engine.  Custom process definition information 
  can be added by adding a <literal>ModuleDefinition</literal> implementation to the process definition.
  When the <literal>ProcessInstance</literal> is created, it will create an instance for every 
  <literal>ModuleDefinition</literal> in the <literal>ProcessDefinition</literal>.  The <literal>ModuleDefinition</literal> is used
  as a factory for <literal>ModuleInstances</literal>.
  </para>
  
  <para>The most integrated way to extend the process definition information is 
  by adding the information to the process archive and implementing a 
  <literal>ProcessArchiveParser</literal>. The <literal>ProcessArchiveParser</literal>
  can parse the information added to the process archive, create your custom 
  <literal>ModuleDefinition</literal> and add it to the <literal>ProcessDefinition</literal>.</para>
  
  <programlisting>public interface ProcessArchiveParser {

  void writeToArchive(ProcessDefinition processDefinition, ProcessArchive archive);
  ProcessDefinition readFromArchive(ProcessArchive archive, ProcessDefinition processDefinition);

}</programlisting>
  
  <para>To do its work, the custom <literal>ModuleInstance</literal> must be notified of 
  relevant events during process execution.  The custom <literal>ModuleDefinition</literal> 
  might add <literal>ActionHandler</literal>  implementations upon events in the process that 
  serve as callback handlers for these process events.</para>

  <para>Alternatively, a custom module might use AOP to bind the custom instance into the 
  process execution.  JBoss AOP is very well suited for this job since it is mature, easy 
  to learn and also part of the JBoss stack.</para>
  
</chapter>