<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "jBPM_Reference_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="security">
  <title>Security</title>
  
  <para>Security features of jBPM are still in alpha stage. This chapter 
  documents the pluggable authentication and authorization.  And what
  parts of the framework are finished and what parts not yet.</para>
  
  <section id="securitytodos">
    <title>Todos</title>
    <para>On the framework part, we still need to define a set of permissions
    that are verified by the jbpm engine while a process is being executed.
    Currently you can check your own permissions, but there is not yet a jbpm 
    default set of permissions.</para>
    <para>Only one default authentication implementation is finished.  Other 
    authentication implementations are envisioned, but not yet implemented.
    Authorization is optional, and there is no authorization implementation 
    yet.  Also for authorization, there are a number of authorization implementations
    envisioned, but they are not yet worked out.
    </para>
    <para>But for both authentication and authorization, the framework is there
    to plug in your own authentication and authorization mechanism.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="authentication">
    <title>Authentication</title>
    <para>Authentication is the process of knowing on who's behalf the code 
    is running.  In case of jBPM this information should be made available from the 
    environment to jBPM.  Cause jBPM is always executed in a specific environment like
    a webapp, an EJB, a swing application or some other environment, it is always the 
    surrounding environment that should perform authentication.</para>
    <para>In a few situations, jBPM needs to know who is running the code.  E.g. to add 
    authentication information in the process logs to know who did what and when. Another 
    example is calculation of an actor based on the current authenticated actor.</para>
    <para>In each situation where jBPM needs to know who is running the code, the 
    central method <literal>org.jbpm.security.Authentication.getAuthenticatedActorId()</literal>
    is called.  That method will delegate to an implementation of 
    <literal>org.jbpm.security.authenticator.Authenticator</literal>.  By specifying an
    implementation of the authenticator, you can configure how jBPM retrieves the currently
    authenticated actor from the environment.
    </para>
    <para>The default authenticator is 
    <literal>org.jbpm.security.authenticator.JbpmDefaultAuthenticator</literal>.
    That implementation will maintain a <literal>ThreadLocal</literal> stack of authenticated 
    actorId's.  Authenticated blocks can be marked with the methods 
    <literal>JbpmDefaultAuthenticator.pushAuthenticatedActorId(String)</literal> and 
    <literal>JbpmDefaultAuthenticator.popAuthenticatedActorId()</literal>.  Be sure to always 
    put these demarcations in a try-finally block.  For the push and pop methods of this 
    authenticator implementation, there are convenience methods supplied on the base 
    Authentication class.  The reason that the JbpmDefaultAuthenticator maintains a stack
    of actorIds instead of just one actorId is simple: it allows the jBPM code to distinct
    between code that is executed on behalf of the user and code that is executed on behalf of 
    the jbpm engine.</para>
    <para>See the javadocs for more information.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="authorization">
    <title>Authorization</title>
    <para>Authorization is validating if an authenticated user is allowed to perform a 
    secured operation.</para>
    <para>The jBPM engine and user code can verify if a user is allowed to perform a given 
    operation with the API method <literal>org.jbpm.security.Authorization.checkPermission(Permission)</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>The Authorization class will also delegate that call to a configurable implementation.
    The interface for pluggin in different authorization strategies is 
    <literal>org.jbpm.security.authorizer.Authorizer</literal>.</para>
    <para>In the package org.jbpm.security.authorizer there are some examples that show intentions 
    of authorizer implementations.  Most are not fully implemented and none of them are tested.</para>
    <para>Also still todo is the definition of a set of jBPM permissions and the verification of 
    those permissions by the jBPM engine.  An example could be verifying that the current authenticated 
    user has sufficient privileges to end a task by calling 
    <literal>Authorization.checkPermission(new TaskPermission("end", Long.toString(id)))</literal>
    in the TaskInstance.end() method.</para>
  </section>

</chapter>
