<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <para>JBoss jBPM is a flexible, extensible framework for process languages. jPDL is
  one process language that is build on top of that common framework.  It is an intuitive 
  process language to express business processes graphically in terms 
  of tasks, wait states for asynchronous communication, timers, automated actions,...
  To bind these operations together, jPDL has the most powerful and extensible 
  control flow mechanism.</para>
  
  <para>jPDL has minimal dependencies and can be used as easy as using a java library.
  But it can also be used in environments where extreme throughput is crucial by 
  deploying it on a J2EE clustered application server. </para>
  
  <para>jPDL can be configured with any database and it can be deployed on any 
  application server.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>The core workflow and BPM functionality is packaged as a simple java library.
    This library includes a service to manage and execute processes in the jPDL 
    database.</para>
    <figure id="overview.image">
      <title>Overview of the jPDL components</title>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/overview.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The jPDL suite</title>
    <para>The suite is a download that contains all the jBPM components bundled in one easy
    download.  The download includes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">config</emphasis>, configuration files for a standard java environment</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">db</emphasis>, SQL scripts for DB creation and compatibility information</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">designer</emphasis>, the eclipse plugin to author jPDL processes and installation scripts (this is not part of the plain jpdl download) See also <xref linkend="jpdlgraphicalprocessdesigner"/>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">doc</emphasis>, userguide and javadocs</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">examples</emphasis></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">lib</emphasis>, libraries on which jbpm depends.  For more information on this see <xref linkend="thirdpartylibraries" /></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">server</emphasis>, a pre-configured jboss that contains jbpm inside the console web application (this is not part of the plain jpdl download)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">src</emphasis>, the jbpm and identity component java sources</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>The pre-configured JBoss application server has the following components installed :
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">web console</emphasis>, packaged as a web archive. That console can be 
      used by process participants as well as jBPM administrators.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">job executor</emphasis> enacts timers and asynchronous messages. There is
      a servlet context listener in the console web app that launches the job executor, which  
      spawns a thread pool for monitoring and executing timers and asynchronous messages.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">jBPM database</emphasis>, an in-process hypersonic database that 
      contains the jBPM tables.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>One <emphasis role="bold">example process</emphasis> is already deployed into the jBPM database.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">Identity component</emphasis> libraries are part of 
      the console web application.  The tables of the identity component are available in the database (those are the tables 
      that start with JBPM_ID_)</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section id="jpdlgraphicalprocessdesigner">
    <title>The jPDL graphical process designer</title>
    <para>jPDL also includes a graphical designer tool.  The designer is a 
    graphical tool for authoring business processes.  It's an eclipse plugin.</para>
    <para>The most important feature of the graphical designer tool is that it 
    includes support for both the business analyst as well as the 
    technical developer.  This enables a smooth transition from business process 
    modeling to the practical implementation.</para>
    <para>The plugin is available as a local update site (plain zip file) for 
    installation via the standard eclipse software updates mechanism.  The 
    jPDL graphical process designer plugin is also included in 
    <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/tools/">JBoss Tools</ulink>, 
    <ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/developer_studio/">JBoss Developer Studio</ulink> and 
    the <ulink url="http://www.jboss.com/products/platforms/soa/">SOA Platform</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The jBPM console web application</title>
    <para>The jBPM console web application serves two purposes.  First, it serves as a central 
    user interface for interacting with runtime tasks generated by the process 
    executions.  Secondly, it is an administration and monitoring console that allows to 
    inspect and manipulate runtime instances.  The third functionality is Business Activity 
    Monitoring.  These are statistics about process executions.  This is useful information 
    for managers to find bottlenecks or other kinds of optimizations.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>The jBPM core library</title>
    <para>The JBoss jBPM core component is the plain java (J2SE) library for managing 
    process definitions and the runtime environment for execution of process instances.
    </para>
    <para>JBoss jBPM is a java library.  As a consequence, it can be used in any java 
    environment like e.g. a web application, a swing application, an EJB, a webservice,...
    The jBPM library can also be packaged and exposed as a stateless session EJB.  This
    allows clustered deployment and scalability for extreme high throughput.  The stateless
    session EJB will be written against the J2EE 1.4 specifications so that it is 
    deployable on any application server.
    </para>
    <para>Depending on the functionality that you use, the library <literal>lib/jbpm-jpdl.jar</literal> 
    has some dependencies on other third party libraries such as e.g. hibernate, dom4j
    and others.  We have done great efforts to require only those dependent libraries that 
    you actually use.  The dependencies are further documented in <xref linkend="deployment" /></para>
    <para>For its persistence, jBPM uses hibernate internally.  Apart from traditional 
    O/R mapping, hibernate also resolves the SQL dialect differences between the different 
    databases, making jBPM portable across all current databases.</para>
    <para>The JBoss jBPM API can be accessed from any custom java software in your 
    project, like e.g. your web application, your EJB's, your web service components, 
    your message driven beans or any other java component.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The JBoss jBPM identity component</title>
    <para>JBoss jBPM can integrate with any company directory that contains users and other 
    organizational information.  But for projects where no organizational information component 
    is readily available, JBoss jBPM includes this component.  The model used in the identity 
    component is richer than the traditional servlet-, ejb- and portlet models.</para>
    <para>For more information, see <xref linkend="theidentitycomponent" /></para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>The JBoss jBPM Job Executor</title>
    <para>The job executor is a component for monitoring and executing jobs in 
    a standard Java environment.  Jobs are used for timers and asynchronous messages.  In an 
    enterprise environment, JMS and the EJB Timer Service can be used for that purpose.  Conversely,
    the job executor can be used in an environment where neither JMS nor EJB are available.
    </para>
    <para>The job executor component is packaged in the core jbpm-jpdl library, but it needs 
    to be deployed in one of the following ways: either register the <literal>JobExecutorLauncher</literal>
    servlet context listener in the web app deployment descriptor to start/stop the job
    executor during creation/destruction of the servlet context, or start up a separate JVM
    and start the job executor in there programatically.</para>
  </section>

</chapter>
