<chapter id="mail">
  <title>Email support</title>
  
  <para>This chapter describes the out-of-the-box email support in jBPM jPDL.
  </para> 

  <section id="mailinjpdl">
    <title>Mail in jPDL</title>
    
    <para>There are four ways of specifying when emails should be sent from a process.
    </para>

    <section id="mailaction">
      <title>Mail action</title>
      <para>A mail action can be used when the sending of this email should not
      be shown as a node in the process graph.
      </para>
      <para>Anywhere you are allowed to specify actions in the process, you can specify a mail action 
      like this:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;mail actors="#{president}" subject="readmylips" text="nomoretaxes" /&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>The subject and text attributes can also be specified as an element like this:</para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;mail actors="#{president}" &gt;
  &lt;subject&gt;readmylips&lt;/subject&gt;
  &lt;text&gt;nomoretaxes&lt;/text&gt;
&lt;/mail&gt;
      </programlisting>
      <para>Each of the fields can contain JSF like expressions.  For example:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;mail to='#{initiator}' subject='websale' text='your websale of #{quantity} #{item} was approved' /&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>For more information about expressions, see <xref linkend="expressions" />.
      </para>
      <para>There are two attribute to specify recipients: <literal>actors</literal> and 
      <literal>to</literal>.  The <literal>to</literal> attribute should resolve to a semicolon
      separated list of email addresses.  The <literal>actors</literal> attribute should resolve to a 
      semicolon separated list of actorIds. Those actorIds will be resolved to email addresses with by 
      means of address resolving<footnote><para><xref linkend="addressresolving"/>.</para></footnote>.
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;mail to='admin@mycompany.com' subject='urgent' text='the mailserver is down :-)' /&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>For more about how to specify recipients, see <xref linkend="specifyingmailrecipients" /></para>
      <para>Mails can be defined in templates and in the process you can overwrite properties of the 
      templates like this:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;mail template='sillystatement' actors="#{president}" /&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>More about templates can be found in <xref linkend="mailtemplates" /></para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="mailnode">
      <title>Mail node</title>
      <para>Just the same as with mail actions, sending of an email can also be modeled as a node.
        In that case, the runtime behavior is just the same, but the email will show up as a node 
        in the process graph.
      </para>
      <para>The attributes and elements supported by mail nodes are exactly the same as with 
      the mail actions<footnote><para><xref linkend="mailaction"/>.</para></footnote>.
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;mail-node name="send email" to="#{president}" subject="readmylips" text="nomoretaxes"&gt;
  &lt;transition to="the next node" /&gt;
&lt;/mail-node&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>Mail nodes should have exactly one leaving transition.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="taskassignmails">
      <title>Task assign mails</title>
      <para>A notification email can be send when a task gets assigned to an actor.  Just use 
      the <literal>notify="yes"</literal> attribute on a task like this:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;task-node name='a'&gt;
  &lt;task name='laundry' swimlane="grandma" notify='yes' /&gt;
  &lt;transition to='b' /&gt;
&lt;/task-node&gt;
</programlisting>
      <para>Setting notify to yes, true or on will cause jBPM to send an email to 
      the actor that will be assigned to this task.  The email is based on a template (see 
      <xref linkend="mailtemplates" />) and contains a link to the task page of the web application.
      </para>
    </section>
  
    <section id="taskremindermails">
      <title>Task reminder mails</title>
      <para>Similarly as with assignments, emails can be sent as a task reminder. The <literal>reminder</literal> 
      element in jPDL is based upon the timer.  The most common attributes will be the <literal>duedate</literal> 
      and the <literal>repeat</literal>. The only difference is that no action has to be specified.
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;task-node name='a'&gt;
  &lt;task name='laundry' swimlane="grandma" notify='yes'&gt;
    &lt;reminder duedate="2 business days" repeat="2 business hours"/&gt;
  &lt;/task&gt;
  &lt;transition to='b' /&gt;
&lt;/task-node&gt;
</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="expressionsinmails">
    <title>Expressions in mails</title>
    <para>The fields <literal>to</literal>, <literal>recipients</literal>, <literal>subject</literal>
    and <literal>text</literal> can contain JSF-like expressions.  For more information about expressions, 
    see <xref linkend="expressions" />
    </para>
    <para>The variables in the expressions can be : swimlanes, process variables, transient variables 
    beans configured in the jbpm.cfg.xml, ...
    </para>
    <para>These expressions can be combined with the address resolving<footnote><para><xref linkend="addressresolving"/>.</para></footnote> 
    that is explained later in this chapter.  For example, suppose that you have a swimlane called president in 
    your process, then look at the following mail specification:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;mail actors="#{president}" subject="readmylips" text="nomoretaxes" /&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>That will send an email to to the person that acts as the president for that particular process 
    execution.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="specifyingmailrecipients">
    <title>Specifying mail recipients</title>
    <section id="multiplerecipients">
      <title>Multiple recipients</title>
      <para>In the <literal>actors</literal> and <literal>to</literal> fields, multiple recipients 
      can be separated with a semi colon (;) or a colon (:).</para>
    </section>
    <section id="BCC">
      <title>Sending Mails to a BCC target</title>
      <para>Sometimes you want to send emails to a BCC target in addition to the normal receipient.
      Currently, there are two supported ways of doing that: First you can specify an <literal>bccActors</literal> 
      or <literal>bcc</literal> attribute (according to <literal>actors</literal> and <literal>to</literal>) in the process definition.
      <programlisting>&lt;mail to='#{initiator}' bcc='bcc@mycompany.com' subject='websale' text='your websale of #{quantity} #{item} was approved' /&gt;</programlisting>
      
      
      The second way is to always send an BCC Mail to some location you can configure in the central configuration (jbpm.cfg.xml) in a property:
          <programlisting>&lt;jbpm-configuration&gt;
  ...
  <emphasis role="bold">&lt;string name="jbpm.mail.bcc.address" value="bcc@mycompany.com" /&gt;</emphasis>
&lt;/jbpm-configuration&gt;</programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="addressresolving">
      <title>Address resolving</title>
      <para>In all of jBPM, actors are referenced by actorId's.  This is a string that serves as the identifier 
      of the process participant.   An address resolver translates actorId's into email addresses.
      </para>
      <para>Use the attribute actors in case you want to apply address resolving 
      and use the attribute to in case you are specifying email addresses 
      directly and don't want to apply address resolving.
      </para>
      <para>An address resolver should implement the following interface:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="java">public interface AddressResolver extends Serializable {
  Object resolveAddress(String actorId);
}</programlisting>
      <para>An address resolver should return 1 of 3 types: a String, a Collection of Strings or an array
      of Strings.  All strings should represent email addresses for the given actorId.
      </para>
      <para>The address resolver implementation should be a bean configured in the jbpm.cfg.xml with 
      name <literal>jbpm.mail.address.resolver</literal> like this:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;jbpm-configuration&gt;
  &lt;bean name='jbpm.mail.address.resolver' class='org.jbpm.identity.mail.IdentityAddressResolver' singleton='true' /&gt;
&lt;/jbpm-configuration&gt;
      </programlisting>
      <para>The identity component of jBPM includes an address resolver.  That address resolver 
      will look for the User of the given actorId.  If the user exists, the user's email is returned,
      otherwise null.  More on the identity component can be found in <xref linkend="theidentitycomponent" />.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="mailtemplates">
    <title>Mail templates</title>
    <para>Instead of specifying mails in the processdefinition.xml, mails can be specified in a template 
    file.  When a template is used, each of the fields can still be overwritten in the processdefinition.xml.
    The mail templates should be specified in an XML file like this:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;mail-templates&gt;

  &lt;variable name="BaseTaskListURL" value="http://localhost:8080/jbpm/task?id=" /&gt;

  &lt;mail-template name='task-assign'&gt;
    &lt;actors&gt;#{taskInstance.actorId}&lt;/actors&gt;
    &lt;subject&gt;Task '#{taskInstance.name}'&lt;/subject&gt;
    &lt;text&gt;&lt;![CDATA[Hi,
Task '#{taskInstance.name}' has been assigned to you.
Go for it: #{BaseTaskListURL}#{taskInstance.id}
Thanks.
---powered by JBoss jBPM---]]&gt;&lt;/text&gt;
  &lt;/mail-template&gt;

  &lt;mail-template name='task-reminder'&gt;
    &lt;actors&gt;#{taskInstance.actorId}&lt;/actors&gt;
    &lt;subject&gt;Task '#{taskInstance.name}' !&lt;/subject&gt;
    &lt;text&gt;&lt;![CDATA[Hey,
Don't forget about #{BaseTaskListURL}#{taskInstance.id} 
Get going !
---powered by JBoss jBPM---]]&gt;&lt;/text&gt;
  &lt;/mail-template&gt;

&lt;/mail-templates&gt;    
    </programlisting>
    <para>As you can see in this example (BaseTaskListURL), extra variables can be defined in 
    the mail templates that will be available in the expressions.
    </para>
    <para>The resource that contains the templates should be configured in the jbpm.cfg.xml
    like this:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;jbpm-configuration&gt;
  &lt;string name="resource.mail.templates" value="jbpm.mail.templates.xml" /&gt;
&lt;/jbpm-configuration&gt;</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="mailserverconfiguration">
    <title>Mail server configuration</title>
    <para>The simplest way to configure the mail server is with the configuration property 
    <literal>jbpm.mail.smtp.host</literal> in the jbpm.cfg.xml like this:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;jbpm-configuration&gt;
  &lt;string name="jbpm.mail.smtp.host" value="localhost" /&gt;
&lt;/jbpm-configuration&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>Alternatively, when more properties need to be specified, a resource reference to 
    a properties file can be given with the key '' like this:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;jbpm-configuration&gt;
  &lt;string name='resource.mail.properties' value='jbpm.mail.properties' /&gt;
&lt;/jbpm-configuration&gt;</programlisting>
    
  </section>

  <section id="fromaddressconfiguration">
    <title>From address configuration</title>
    <para>The default value for the From address used in jPDL mails is <literal>jbpm@noreply</literal>.  
    The from address of mails can be configured in the jBPM configuration file jbpm.xfg.xml with 
    key 'jbpm.mail.from.address' like this:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;jbpm-configuration&gt;
  &lt;string name='jbpm.mail.from.address' value='jbpm@yourcompany.com' /&gt;
&lt;/jbpm-configuration&gt;</programlisting>
  </section>
  
  <section id="customizingmailsupport">
    <title>Customizing mail support</title>
    <para>All the mail support in jBPM is centralized in one class: <literal>org.jbpm.mail.Mail</literal>
    This is an ActionHandler implementation.  Whenever an mail is specified in the process xml, this will 
    result in a delegation to the mail class.  It is possible to inherit from the Mail class and customize 
    certain behavior for your particular needs.  To configure your class to be used for mail delegations, 
    specify a 'jbpm.mail.class.name' configuration string in the jbpm.cfg.xml like this:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;jbpm-configuration&gt;
  &lt;string name='jbpm.mail.class.name' value='com.your.specific.CustomMail' /&gt;
&lt;/jbpm-configuration&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>The customized mail class will be read during parsing and actions will be configured in the 
    process that reference the configured (or the default) mail classname.  So if you change the 
    property, all the processes that were already deployed will still refer to the old mail class name.
    But they can be easily updated with one simple update statement to the jbpm database.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="mailserver">
    <title>Mail server</title>
    <para>If you need a mail server that is easy to install, check out <ulink url="http://buni.org/">Meldware</ulink>
    or <ulink url="http://james.apache.org/">Apache James</ulink>
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>