<chapter id="processmodelling">
  <title>Process Modeling</title>
  
  <section id="overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    
    <para>A process definition represents a formal specification of a business process and 
    is based on a directed graph.  The graph is composed of nodes and transitions. Every 
    node in the graph is of a specific type.  The type of the node defines the runtime 
    behavior.  A process definition has exactly one start state.</para>
    
    <para>A token is one path of execution.  A token is the runtime concept that maintains 
    a pointer to a node in the graph.</para>
    
    <para>A process instance is one execution of a process definition. When a process instance 
    is created, a token is created for the main path of execution.  This token is called the 
    root token of the process instance and it is positioned in the start state of the process
    definition.</para>
    
    <para>A signal instructs a token to continue graph execution.  When receiving an unnamed 
    signal, the token will leave its current node over the default leaving transition.  When 
    a transition-name is specified in the signal, the token will leave its node over the 
    specified transition.  A signal given to the process instance is delegated to the 
    root token.</para>
 
    <para>After the token has entered a node, the node is executed.  Nodes themselves are
    responsible for the continuation of the graph execution.  Continuation of graph execution 
    is done by making the token leave the node.  Each node type can implement a different 
    behavior for the continuation of the graph execution.  A node that does not propagate 
    execution will behave as a state.</para>
    
    <para>Actions are pieces of java code that are executed upon events in the process 
    execution.    The graph is an important instrument in the communication about software 
    requirements. But the graph is just one view (projection) of the software being produced.  
    It hides many technical details.  Actions are a mechanism to add technical details outside 
    of the graphical representation. Once the graph is put in place, it can be decorated with 
    actions.  The main event types are entering a node, leaving a node and taking a 
    transition.</para>
	<!-- same paragraph again below?? -->
  </section>
  
  <section id="processgraph">
    <title>Process graph</title>
    <para>The basis of a process definition is a graph that is made up of nodes and transitions.
    That information is expressed in an xml file called <literal>processdefinition.xml</literal>.
    Each node has a type like e.g. state, decision, fork, join,...  Each node has a set of leaving 
    transitions. A name can be given to the transitions that leave a node in order to make them distinct. 
    For example: The following diagram shows a process graph of the jBAY auction process.</para>

    <figure id="auction.process.graph.image">
      <title>The auction process graph</title>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/auction.process.graph.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Below is the process graph of the jBAY auction process represented as xml:</para>
<programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition&gt;

  &lt;start-state&gt;
    &lt;transition to="auction" /&gt;
  &lt;/start-state&gt;
  
  &lt;state name="auction"&gt;
    &lt;transition name="auction ends" to="salefork" /&gt;
    &lt;transition name="cancel" to="end" /&gt;
  &lt;/state&gt;
  
  &lt;fork name="salefork"&gt;
    &lt;transition name="shipping" to="send item" /&gt;
    &lt;transition name="billing" to="receive money" /&gt;
  &lt;/fork&gt;
  
  &lt;state name="send item"&gt;
    &lt;transition to="receive item" /&gt;
  &lt;/state&gt;

  &lt;state name="receive item"&gt;
    &lt;transition to="salejoin" /&gt;
  &lt;/state&gt;
  
  &lt;state name="receive money"&gt;
    &lt;transition to="send money" /&gt;
  &lt;/state&gt;

  &lt;state name="send money"&gt;
    &lt;transition to="salejoin" /&gt;
  &lt;/state&gt;
  
  &lt;join name="salejoin"&gt;
    &lt;transition to="end" /&gt;
  &lt;/join&gt;
  
  &lt;end-state name="end" /&gt;
  
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="nodes">
    <title>Nodes</title>
    <para>A process graph is made up of nodes and transitions.
    Each node has a specific type.  The node type determines what will happen when 
    an execution arrives in the node at runtime.  jBPM has a set of   node types 
    that you can use.  Alternatively, you can write custom code for implementing your own specific 
    node behavior.</para>
    
    <section id="noderesponsibilities">
      <title>Node responsibilities</title>
      <para>Each node has 2 main responsibilities: First, it can execute plain java code. 
      Typically the plain java code relates to the function of the node.  E.g. creating a 
      few task instances, sending a notification, updating a database,...  Secondly, a node 
      is responsible for propagating the process execution.  Basically, each node has the 
      following options for propagating the process execution:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">1. not propagate the execution.</emphasis>  In that 
        case the node behaves as a wait state.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">2. propagate the execution over one of the leaving 
        transitions of the node.</emphasis>  This means that the token that originally 
        arrived in the node is passed over one of the leaving transitions with the API call
        executionContext.leaveNode(String).  The node will now act as an automatic node in the 
        sense it can execute some custom programming logic and then continue process execution 
        automatically without waiting.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">3. create new paths of execution.</emphasis> A node can
        decide to create new tokens.  Each new token represents a new path of execution and 
        each new token can be launched over the node's leaving transitions. A good example of 
        this kind of behavior is the fork node.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">4. end paths of execution.</emphasis> A node can decide
        to end a path of execution. That means that the token is ended and the path of execution
        is finished.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">5. more general, a node can modify the whole runtime 
        structure of the process instance.</emphasis>  The runtime structure is a process instance 
        that contains a tree of tokens.  Each token represents a path of execution.  A node can 
        create and end tokens, put each token in a node of the graph and launch tokens over 
        transitions.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>jBPM contains --as any workflow and BPM engine-- a set of pre-implemented node types
      that have a specific documented configuration and behavior.  But the unique thing about 
      jBPM and the Graph Oriented Programming foundation
      is that we open up the model for developers.  Developers can write their own node behavior
      very easily and use it in a process.
      </para>
      <para>That is where traditional workflow and BPM systems are
      much more closed.  They usually supply a fixed set of node types (called the process language).
      Their process language is closed and the execution model is hidden in the runtime 
      environment.  Research of <ulink url="http://www.workflowpatterns.com">workflow patterns</ulink>
      has shown that any process language is not powerful enough.  We have decided for a simple 
      model and allow developers to write their own node types.  That way the JPDL process language 
      is open ended.</para>
      <para>Next, we discuss the most important node types of JPDL.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="nodetypetasknode">
      <title>Nodetype task-node</title>
      <para>A task node represents one or more tasks that are to be performed by humans.
      So when execution arrives in a task node, task instances will be created in the task 
      lists of the workflow participants.  After that, the node will behave as a wait state.
      So when the users perform their task, the task completion will trigger the resuming 
      of the execution. In other words, that leads to a new signal being called on the token.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="nodetypetaskstate">
      <title>Nodetype state</title>
      <para>A state is a bare-bones wait state.  The difference with a task node is that 
      no task instances will be created in any task list.  This can be useful if the process 
      should wait for an external system.  E.g. upon entry of the node (via an action on the node-enter
      event), a message could be sent to the external system.  After that, the process will
      go into a wait state.  When the external system send a response message, this can lead to 
      a token.signal(), which triggers resuming of the process execution.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="nodetypedecision">
      <title>Nodetype decision</title>
      <para>Actually there are 2 ways to model a decision.  The distinction between the two 
      is based on *who* is making the decision.  Should the decision made by the process (read:
      specified in the process definition).  Or should an external entity provide the result of 
      the decision.</para>
      <para>When the decision is to be taken by the process, a decision node should be used.
      There are basically 2 ways to specify the decision criteria.  Simplest is by adding 
      condition elements on the transitions.  Conditions are EL expressions or beanshell scripts
      that return a boolean.</para>
      <para>At runtime the decision node will FIRST loop over its leaving transitions THAT HAVE 
      a condition specified.  It will evaluate those transitions first in 
      the order as specified in the xml.  The first transition for which the condition resolves to 
      'true' will be taken.  If all transitions with a condition resolve to false, the default 
      transition (the first in the XML) is taken.</para>
      <para>Another approach is to use an expression that returns the name 
      of the transition to take.  With the 'expression' attribute, you can specify an expression
      on the decision that has to resolve to one of the leaving transitions of the decision node.</para>
      <para>Next approach is the 'handler' element on the decision, that element can be used to specify
      an implementation of the DecisionHandler interface can be specified on the decision node.  Then the 
      decision is calculated in a java class and the selected leaving transition is returned by the decide-method 
      of the DecisionHandler implementation.</para>
      <para>When the decision is taken by an external party (meaning: not part of the process 
      definition), you should use multiple transitions leaving a state or wait state node.
      Then the leaving transition can be provided in the external trigger that resumes execution
      after the wait state is finished.  E.g. <literal>Token.signal(String transitionName)</literal> 
      and <literal>TaskInstance.end(String transitionName)</literal>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="nodetypefork">
      <title>Nodetype fork</title>
      <para>A fork splits one path of execution into multiple concurrent paths of execution.  The 
      default fork behavior is to create a child token for each transition that leaves the fork,
      creating a parent-child relation between the token that arrives in the fork.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="nodetypejoin">
      <title>Nodetype join</title>
      <para>The default join assumes that all tokens that arrive in the join are children of the
      same parent.  This situation is created when using the fork as mentioned above and when all 
      tokens created by a fork arrive in the same join. A join will end every token that enters the 
      join.  Then the join will examine the parent-child relation of the token that enters the 
      join.  When all sibling tokens have arrived in the join, the parent token will be propagated 
      over the (unique!) leaving transition.  When there are still sibling tokens active, the join
      will behave as a wait state.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="nodetypenode">
      <title>Nodetype node</title>
      <para>The type node serves the situation where you want to write your own code in a node.
      The nodetype node expects one sub-element action.  The action is executed when the execution
      arrives in the node.  The code you write in the actionhandler can do anything you want but 
      it is also responsible for propagating the execution<footnote><para><xref linkend="noderesponsibilities"/>.</para></footnote>.
      </para>
      <para>This node can be used if you want to use a JavaAPI to implement some functional logic that 
      is important for the business analyst.  By using a node, the node is visible in the graphical
      representation of the process.  For comparison, actions --covered next-- will allow you to 
      add code that is invisible in the graphical representation of the process, in case that logic 
      is not important for the business analyst.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="transitions">
    <title>Transitions</title>
    <para>Transitions have a source node and a destination node.  The source node is represented with 
      the property <literal>from</literal> and the destination node is represented by the property
      <literal>to</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>A transition can optionally have a name.  Note that most of the jBPM features depend on the uniqueness
      of the transition name.  If more than one transition has the same name, the first transition with 
      the given name is taken.  In case duplicate transition names occur in a node, the method 
      <literal>Map getLeavingTransitionsMap()</literal> will return less elements than  
      <literal>List getLeavingTransitions()</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>The default transition is the first transition in the list.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="actions">
    <title>Actions</title>
    <para>Actions are pieces of java code that are executed upon events in the process 
    execution. The graph is an important instrument in the communication about software 
    requirements. But the graph is just one view (projection) of the software being produced.  
    It hides many technical details.  Actions are a mechanism to add technical details outside 
    of the graphical representation. Once the graph is put in place, it can be decorated with 
    actions.  This means that java code can be associated with the graph without changing the 
    structure of the graph. The main event types are entering a node, leaving a node and taking a 
    transition.</para>
    
    <para>Note the difference between an action that is placed in an event versus an action 
    that is placed in a node.  Actions that are put in an event are executed when the event 
    fires.  Actions on events have no way to influence the flow of control of the process. 
    It is similar to the observer pattern.  On the other hand, an action that is put on a 
    node<footnote><para><xref linkend="nodetypenode"/>.</para></footnote> has the responsibility 
    of propagating the execution<footnote><para><xref linkend="noderesponsibilities"/>.</para></footnote>.</para>

    <para>Let's look at an example of an action on an event.  Suppose we want to do a database 
    update on a given transition.  The database update is technically vital but it is not important 
    to the business analyst.</para>
    
    <figure id="database.update.example.image">
      <title>A database update action</title>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/database.update.example.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <programlisting language="java">public class RemoveEmployeeUpdate implements ActionHandler {
  public void execute(ExecutionContext ctx) throws Exception {
    // get the fired employee from the process variables.
    String firedEmployee = (String) ctx.getContextInstance().getVariable("fired employee");
    
    // by taking the same database connection as used for the jbpm updates, we 
    // reuse the jbpm transaction for our database update.
    Connection connection = ctx.getProcessInstance().getJbpmSession().getSession().getConnection();
    Statement statement = connection.createStatement();
    statement.execute("DELETE FROM EMPLOYEE WHERE ...");
    statement.execute(); 
    statement.close();
  }
}</programlisting>
    
<programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition name="yearly evaluation"&gt;
  &lt;state name="fire employee"&gt;
    &lt;transition to="collect badge"&gt;
      &lt;action class="com.nomercy.hr.RemoveEmployeeUpdate" />
    &lt;/transition&gt;
  &lt;/state&gt;
  
  &lt;state name="collect badge"&gt;
  
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>

    <section id="actionconfiguration">
      <title>Action configuration</title>
	    <para>For more information about adding configurations to your custom actions and how 
	    to specify the configuration in the <literal>processdefinition.xml</literal>, 
	    see <xref linkend="configurationofdelegations"/>
	    </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="actionreferences">
      <title>Action references</title>
      <para>Actions can be given a name.  Named actions can be referenced from other 
      locations where actions can be specified. Named actions can also be put as child 
      elements in the process definition.</para>
      <para>This feature is interesting if you want to limit duplication of action 
      configurations (e.g. when the action has complicated configurations).  Another 
      use case is execution or scheduling of runtime actions.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="events">
      <title>Events</title>
      <para>Events specify moments in the execution of the process.  The jBPM engine 
      will fire events during graph execution.  This occurs when jbpm calculates the 
      next state (read: processing a signal).  An event is always relative to an element 
      in the process definition like e.g. the process definition, a node or a transition.
      Most process elements can fire different types of events.  A node for example can 
      fire a <literal>node-enter</literal> event and a <literal>node-leave</literal>
      event.  Events are the hooks for actions.  Each event has a list of actions.
      When the jBPM engine fires an event, the list of actions is executed.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="eventpropagation">
      <title>Event propagation</title>
      <para>Superstates create a parent-child relation in the elements of a process definition.
      Nodes and transitions contained in a superstate have that superstate as a parent.  Top level 
      elements have the process definition as a parent.  The process definition does not have a 
      parent.  When an event is fired, the event will be propagated up the parent hierarchy.
      This allows e.g. to capture all transition events in a process and associate actions 
      with these events in a centralized location.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="script">
      <title>Script</title>
      <para>A script is an action that executes a beanshell script.  For more information about beanshell, 
      see <ulink url="http://www.beanshell.org/">the beanshell website</ulink>.  
      By default, all process variables are available as script-variables and no script-variables will be 
      written to the process variables.  Also the following script-variables will be available :
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>executionContext</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>token</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>node</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>task</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>taskInstance</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
<programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition&gt;
  &lt;event type="node-enter"&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
      System.out.println("this script is entering node "+node);
    &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/event&gt;
  ...
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>To customize the default behavior of loading and storing variables into the script, the 
      <literal>variable</literal> element can be used as a sub-element of script.  In that case,
      the script expression also has to be put in a sub-element of script: <literal>expression</literal>.  
      </para>

<programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition&gt;
  &lt;event type="process-end"&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
      &lt;expression&gt;
        a = b + c;
      &lt;/expression&gt;
      &lt;variable name='XXX' access='write' mapped-name='a' /&gt;
      &lt;variable name='YYY' access='read' mapped-name='b' /&gt;
      &lt;variable name='ZZZ' access='read' mapped-name='c' /&gt;
    &lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/event&gt;
  ...
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Before the script starts, the process variables <literal>YYY</literal> and 
      <literal>ZZZ</literal> will be made available to the script as script-variables
      <literal>b</literal> and <literal>c</literal> respectively.  After the script is 
      finished, the value of script-variable <literal>a</literal> is stored into the 
      process variable <literal>XXX</literal>.</para>

      <para>If the <literal>access</literal> attribute of <literal>variable</literal> contains 
      '<literal>read</literal>', the 
      process variable will be loaded as a script-variable before script evaluation.  If the 
      <literal>access</literal> attribute contains '<literal>write</literal>', the script-variable 
      will be stored as a process variable after evaluation.
      The attribute <literal>mapped-name</literal> can make the process variable available under another
      name in the script.  This can be handy when your process variable names contain spaces or other 
      invalid script-literal-characters.
      </para>
      
    </section>

    <section id="customevents">
      <title>Custom events</title>
      <para>Note that it's possible to fire your own custom events at will during the 
      execution of a process.  Events are uniquely defined by the combination of a graph 
      element (nodes, transitions, process definitions and superstates are graph elements)
      and an event-type (java.lang.String).  jBPM defines a set of events that are fired for 
      nodes, transitions and other graph elements.  But as a user, you are free to fire your 
      own events.   In actions, in your own custom node implementations, or even outside the execution 
      of a process instance, you can call the <literal>GraphElement.fireEvent(String eventType, 
      ExecutionContext executionContext);</literal>.  The names of the event types can 
      be chosen freely.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="superstates">
    <title>Superstates</title>
    <para>A Superstate is a group of nodes.  Superstates can be nested recursively.  Superstates 
    can be used to bring some hierarchy in the process definition.  For example, one application 
    could be to group all the nodes of a process in phases.  Actions can be associated with 
    superstate events.  A consequence is that a token can be in multiple nested nodes at a given
    time.  This can be convenient to check whether a process execution is e.g. in the start-up phase.
    In the jBPM model, you are free to group any set of nodes in a superstate.
    </para>
    
    <section id="superstatetransitions">
      <title>Superstate transitions</title>
      <para>All transitions leaving a superstate can be taken by tokens in nodes contained within
      the super state. Transitions can also arrive in superstates.  In that case, the token will be 
      redirected to the first node in the superstate.  Nodes from outside the superstate can have 
      transitions directly to nodes inside the superstate.  Also, the other way round, nodes within 
      superstates can have transitions to nodes outside the superstate or to the superstate itself.  
      Superstates also can have self references.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="superstateevents">
      <title>Superstate events</title>
      <para>There are 2 events unique to superstates: <literal>superstate-enter</literal> and 
      <literal>superstate-leave</literal>.  These events will be fired no matter over which 
      transitions the node is entered or left respectively.  As long as a token takes transitions
      within the superstate, these events are not fired.</para>
   
      <para>Note that we have created separate event types for states and superstates.  This is 
      to make it easy to distinct between superstate events and node events that are propagated 
      from within the superstate.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="hierarchicalnames">
      <title>Hierarchical names</title>
      <para>Node names have to be unique in their scope.  The scope of the node is its node-collection.
      Both the process definition and the superstate are node collections.  To refer to nodes in 
      superstates, you have to specify the relative, slash (/) separated name.  The slash separates 
      the node names. Use '..' to refer to an upper level.  The next example shows how to reference
      a node in a superstate:</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition&gt;
  &lt;state name="preparation"&gt;
    &lt;transition to="phase one/invite murphy"/&gt;
  &lt;/state&gt;
  &lt;super-state name="phase one"&gt;
    &lt;state name="invite murphy"/&gt;
  &lt;/super-state&gt;
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>The next example will show how to go up the superstate hierarchy</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition&gt;
  &lt;super-state name="phase one"&gt;
    &lt;state name="preparation"&gt;
      &lt;transition to="../phase two/invite murphy"/&gt;
    &lt;/state&gt;
  &lt;/super-state&gt;
  &lt;super-state name="phase two"&gt;
    &lt;state name="invite murphy"/&gt;
  &lt;/super-state&gt;
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="exceptionhandling">
    <title>Exception handling</title>
    <para>The exception handling mechanism of jBPM only applies to java exceptions.
    Graph execution on itself cannot result in problems.  It is only the execution 
    of delegation classes that can lead to exceptions.
    </para>
    
    <para>On <literal>process-definition</literal>s, <literal>node</literal>s and 
    <literal>transition</literal>s, a list of <literal>exception-handler</literal>s
    can be specified.  Each <literal>exception-handler</literal> has a list of actions.
    When an exception occurs in a delegation class, the process 
    element parent hierarchy is searched for an appropriate <literal>exception-handler</literal>.
    When it is found, the actions of the <literal>exception-handler</literal> are 
    executed.
    </para>  
    
    <para>Note that the exception handling mechanism of jBPM is not completely similar to 
    the java exception handling.  In java, a caught exception can have an influence on 
    the control flow.  In the case of jBPM, control flow cannot be changed by the 
    jBPM exception handling mechanism.  The exception is either caught or uncaught. 
    Uncaught exceptions are thrown to the client (e.g. the client that called the 
    <literal>token.signal()</literal>) or the exception is caught by a jBPM 
    <literal>exception-handler</literal>.  For caught exceptions, the graph execution 
    continues as if no exception has occurred.</para>
    
    <para>Note that in an <literal>action</literal> that handles an exception, it 
    is possible to put the token in an arbitrary node in the graph with 
    <literal>Token.setNode(Node node)</literal>.
    </para>
  </section>
    
  <section id="modelling_processcomposition">
    <title>Process composition</title>
    <para>Process composition is supported in jBPM by means of the <literal>process-state</literal>.
    The process state is a state that is associated with another process definition.  When graph 
    execution arrives in the process state, a new process instance of the sub-process is created 
    and it is associated with the path of execution that arrived in the process state.  The 
    path of execution of the super process will wait until the sub process instance has ended.
    When the sub process instance ends, the path of execution of the super process will leave 
    the process state and continue graph execution in the super process.
    </para>
    
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition name=&quot;hire&quot;&gt;
  &lt;start-state&gt;
    &lt;transition to=&quot;initial interview&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/start-state&gt;
  &lt;process-state name=&quot;initial interview&quot;&gt;
    &lt;sub-process name=&quot;interview&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;variable name=&quot;a&quot; access=&quot;read,write&quot; mapped-name=&quot;aa&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;variable name=&quot;b&quot; access=&quot;read&quot; mapped-name=&quot;bb&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;transition to=&quot;...&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/process-state&gt;
  ...
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>This 'hire' process contains a <literal>process-state</literal>
    that spawns an 'interview' process. 
    When execution arrives in the 'first interview', a new execution (=process instance) of
    the 'interview' process is created. If no explicit version is specified, the latest version
    of the sub process as known when deploying the 'hire' process is used. To make jBPM
    instantiate a specific version the optional <literal>version</literal> attribute can be
    specified. To postpone binding the specified or latest version until actually creating the
    sub process, the optional <literal>binding</literal> attribute should be set to
    <literal>late</literal>. 
    
    Then variable 'a' from 
    the hire process is copied into variable 'aa' from the interview process.
    The same way, hire variable 'b' is copied into interview variable 'bb'.
    When the interview process finishes, only variable 'aa' from the 
    interview process is copied back into the 'a' variable of the 
    hire process.</para>

    <para>In general, When a sub-process is started, all <literal>variable</literal>s with 
    <literal>read</literal> 
    access are read from the super process and fed into the newly created sub process before the signal 
    is given to leave the start state.  When the sub process instances is finished, all the 
    <literal>variable</literal>s with <literal>write</literal> access will be copied from the sub 
    process to the super process.  The <literal>mapped-name</literal> attribute of the <literal>variable</literal>
    element allows you to specify the variable name that should be used in the sub process.</para>
  </section>
    
  <section id="customnodebehaviour">
    <title>Custom node behavior</title>
    <para>In jBPM, it's quite easy to write your own custom nodes.  For creating custom nodes, an 
    implementation of the ActionHandler has to be written.  The implementation can execute any 
    business logic, but also has the responsibility to propagate the graph execution.  Let's look 
    at an example that will update an ERP-system.  We'll read an amount from the ERP-system, add 
    an amount that is stored in the process variables and store the result back in the ERP-system.
    Based on the size of the amount, we have to leave the node via the 'small amounts' or the 
    'large amounts' transition.
    </para>
    
    <figure id="update.erp.example.image">
      <title>The update erp example process snippet</title>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/update.erp.example.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <programlisting language="java">public class AmountUpdate implements ActionHandler {
  public void execute(ExecutionContext ctx) throws Exception {
    // business logic
    Float erpAmount = ...get amount from erp-system...;
    Float processAmount = (Float) ctx.getContextInstance().getVariable("amount");
    float result = erpAmount.floatValue() + processAmount.floatValue();
    ...update erp-system with the result...;
    
    // graph execution propagation
    if (result > 5000) {
      ctx.leaveNode(ctx, "big amounts");
    } else {
      ctx.leaveNode(ctx, "small amounts");
    }
  }
}</programlisting>

    <para>It is also possible to create and join tokens in custom node 
    implementations.  For an example on how to do this, check out the Fork and 
    Join node implementation in the jbpm source code.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="graphexecution">
    <title>Graph execution</title>
    <para>The graph execution model of jBPM is based on interpretation of the 
    process definition and the chain of command pattern.</para>
    
    <para>Interpretation of the process definition means that the process 
    definition data is stored in the database.  At runtime the process definition 
    information is used during process execution.  Note for the concerned : 
    we use Hibernate's second level cache to avoid loading of definition information 
    at runtime.  Since the process definitions don't change (see process versioning)
    hibernate can cache the process definitions in memory.</para>
    
    <para>The chain of command pattern means that each node in the graph is 
    responsible for propagating the process execution.  If a node does not 
    propagate execution, it behaves as a wait state.</para>
    
    <para>The idea is to start execution on process instances and that the execution 
    continues till it enters a wait state.</para>
    
    <para>A token represents a path of execution.  A token has a pointer to a node 
    in the process graph.  During wait states, the tokens can be persisted 
    in the database.  Now we are going to look at the algorithm for calculating the 
    execution of a token.  Execution starts when a signal is sent to a token.
    The execution is then passed over the transitions and nodes via the chain of 
    command pattern. These are the relevant methods in a class diagram.</para>
    
    <figure id="graph.execution.image">
      <title>The graph execution related methods</title>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/graph.execution.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>When a token is in a node, signals can be sent to the token.  Sending a 
    signal is an instruction to start execution.  A signal must therefore specify 
    a leaving transition of the token's current node.  The first transition is the 
    default.  In a signal to a token, the token takes its current node 
    and calls the <literal>Node.leave(ExecutionContext,Transition)</literal> method.  Think 
    of the ExecutionContext as a Token because the main object in an ExecutionContext 
    is a Token.  The <literal>Node.leave(ExecutionContext,Transition)</literal> method will 
    fire the <literal>node-leave</literal> event and call the 
    <literal>Transition.take(ExecutionContext)</literal>.  That method will fire 
	the <literal>transition</literal> event and call the 
    <literal>Node.enter(ExecutionContext)</literal> on the destination node of the
    transition.  That method will fire the <literal>node-enter</literal> event and 
    call the <literal>Node.execute(ExecutionContext)</literal>.  Each type of node 
    has its own behaviour that is implemented in the execute method.  Each node 
    is responsible for propagating graph execution by calling the 
    <literal>Node.leave(ExecutionContext,Transition)</literal> again. In summary:</para> 
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Token.signal(Transition)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>--> Node.leave(ExecutionContext,Transition)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>--> Transition.take(ExecutionContext)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>--> Node.enter(ExecutionContext)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>--> Node.execute(ExecutionContext)</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Note that the complete calculation of the next state, including the invocation 
    of the actions is done in the thread of the client.  A common misconception is that 
    all calculations *must* be done in the thread of the client.  As with any asynchronous 
    invocation, you can use asynchronous messaging (JMS) for that.   When the message is 
    sent in the same transaction as the process instance update, all synchronization issues 
    are taken care of.  Some workflow systems use asynchronous messaging between all nodes 
    in the graph.  But in high throughput environments, this algorithm gives much more control 
    and flexibility for tweaking performance of a business process.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="transactiondemarcation">
    <title>Transaction demarcation</title>
    <para>As explained in <xref linkend="graphexecution" />,
    jBPM runs the process in the thread of 
    the client and is by nature synchronous.  Meaning that the <literal>token.signal()</literal>
    or <literal>taskInstance.end()</literal> will only return when the process has entered a new 
    wait state.
    </para>
    <para>The jPDL feature that we describe here from a modeling perspective is 
    <xref linkend="asynchronouscontinuations" />.
    </para>
    <para>In most situations this is the most straightforward approach because the process 
    execution can easily be bound to server side transactions: the process moves from one 
    state to the next in one transaction.
    </para>
    <para>In some scenarios where in-process calculations take a lot of time, this behavior 
    might be undesirable.  To cope with this, jBPM includes an asynchronous messaging system
    that allows to continue a process in an asynchronous manner.  Of course, in a java enterprise 
    environment, jBPM can be configured to use a JMS message broker instead of the built in 
    messaging system.
    </para>
    <para>In any node, jPDL supports the attribute <literal>async=&quot;true&quot;</literal>.
    Asynchronous nodes will not be executed in the thread of the client.  Instead, a message is 
    sent over the asynchronous messaging system and the thread is returned to the client 
    (meaning that the <literal>token.signal()</literal> or <literal>taskInstance.end()</literal> 
    will return).
    </para>
    <para>Note that the jbpm client code can now commit the transaction.  The sending of the 
    message should be done in the same transaction as the process updates.  So the net result of 
    the transaction is that the token has moved to the next node (which has not yet been executed) 
    and a <literal>org.jbpm.command.ExecuteNodeCommand</literal>-message has been sent on the 
    asynchronous messaging system to the jBPM Command Executor.
    </para>
    <para>The jBPM Command Executor reads commands from the queue and executes them.  In the case 
    of the <literal>org.jbpm.command.ExecuteNodeCommand</literal>, the process will be continued 
    with executing the node.  Each command is executed in a separate transaction.
    </para>
    <para>So in order for asynchronous processes to continue, a jBPM Command Executor needs to 
    be running.  The simplest way to do that is to configure the <literal>CommandExecutionServlet</literal>
    in your web application.  Alternatively, you should make sure that the CommandExecutor thread is 
    up and running in any other way.
    </para>
    <para>As a process modeler, you should not really be concerned with all this asynchronous 
    messaging.  The main point to remember is transaction demarcation: By default jBPM will operate
    in the transaction of the client, doing the whole calculation until the process enters a wait 
    state.  Use <literal>async=&quot;true&quot;</literal> to demarcate a transaction in the process.
    </para>
    
    <para>Let's look at an example:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;start-state&gt;
  &lt;transition to=&quot;one&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/start-state&gt;
&lt;node async=&quot;true&quot; name=&quot;one&quot;&gt;
  &lt;action class=&quot;com...MyAutomaticAction&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;transition to=&quot;two&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/node&gt;
&lt;node async=&quot;true&quot; name=&quot;two&quot;&gt;
  &lt;action class=&quot;com...MyAutomaticAction&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;transition to=&quot;three&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/node&gt;
&lt;node async=&quot;true&quot; name=&quot;three&quot;&gt;
  &lt;action class=&quot;com...MyAutomaticAction&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;transition to=&quot;end&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/node&gt;
&lt;end-state name=&quot;end&quot; /&gt;
...</programlisting>
    <para>Client code to interact with process executions (starting and 
    resuming) is exactly the same as with normal (synchronous) processes:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="java">//start a transaction
JbpmContext jbpmContext = jbpmConfiguration.createContext();
try {
  ProcessInstance processInstance = jbpmContext.newProcessInstance("my async process");
  processInstance.signal();
  jbpmContext.save(processInstance);
} finally {
  jbpmContext.close();
}</programlisting>
    <para>After this first transaction, the root token of the process instance 
    will point to node <literal>one</literal> and a 
    <literal>ExecuteNodeCommand</literal>message will have been sent to the 
    command executor.
    </para>
    <para>In a subsequent transaction, the command executor will read the message 
    from the queue and execute node <literal>one</literal>.  The action can decide to 
    propagate the execution or enter a wait state.  If the action decides to propagate 
    the execution, the transaction will be ended when the execution arrives at 
    node two.  And so on, and so on...
    </para>

  </section>
    
</chapter>
