<chapter id="scheduler">
  <title>Scheduler</title>
  <para>This chapter describes how to work with timers in jBPM.</para>
  
  <para>Upon events in the process, timers can be created.  When a timer 
  expires, an action can be executed or a transition can be taken.</para>
  
  <section id="timers">
    <title>Timers</title>
  
    <para>The easiest way to specify a timer is by adding a timer element 
    to the node.</para>
  
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;state name='catch crooks'&gt;
  &lt;timer name='reminder' 
         duedate='3 business hours' 
         repeat='10 business minutes'
         transition='time-out-transition' &gt;
    &lt;action class='the-remainder-action-class-name' /&gt;
  &lt;/timer&gt;
  &lt;transition name='time-out-transition' to='...' /&gt;
&lt;/state&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>A timer that is specified on a node, is not executed after the node 
    is left.  Both the transition and the action are optional.  When a timer 
    is executed, the following events occur in sequence : </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>an event is fired of type <literal>timer</literal></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>if an action is specified, the action is executed.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>if a transition is specified, a signal will be sent to resume execution 
      over the given transition.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>Every timer must have a unique name.  If no name is specified in the 
    <literal>timer</literal> element, the name of the node is taken as the name 
    of the timer.</para>
    
    <para>The timer action can be any supported action element like e.g. 
    <literal>action</literal> or <literal>script</literal>.</para>

    <para>Timers are created and canceled by actions.  The 2 action-elements are 
    <literal>create-timer</literal> and <literal>cancel-timer</literal>. Actually, the 
    timer element shown above is just a short notation for a create-timer action 
    on <literal>node-enter</literal> and a cancel-timer action on 
    <literal>node-leave</literal>.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="schedulerdeployment">
    <title>Scheduler deployment</title>
    
    <para>Process executions create and cancel timers.  The timers are stored in 
    a timer store.  A separate timer runner must check the timer store and execute 
    the timers when they are due.</para>

    <figure id="scheduler.overview.image">
      <title>Scheduler components overview</title>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/scheduler.overview.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
  </section>
    
</chapter>