<chapter id="taskmanagement">

  <title>Task management</title>
  <para>The core business of jBPM is the ability to persist the execution 
  of a process.  A situation in which this feature is extremely useful is 
  the management of tasks and task-lists for people.   jBPM allows to 
  specify a piece of software describing an overall process which 
  can have wait states for human tasks.</para>
  
  <section id="tasks">
    <title>Tasks</title>
    
    <para>Tasks are part of the process definition and they define how 
    task instances must be created and assigned during process 
    executions.</para>
    <para>Tasks can be defined in <literal>task-node</literal>s and in the 
    <literal>process-definition</literal>.  The most common way is to define 
    one or more <literal>task</literal>s in a <literal>task-node</literal>.
    In that case the <literal>task-node</literal> represents a task to be 
    done by the user and the process execution should wait until the actor 
    completes the task.  When the actor completes the task, process execution 
    should continue.  When more tasks are specified in a 
    <literal>task-node</literal>, the default behavior is to wait for all the 
    tasks to complete.
    </para>
    
    <para>Tasks can also be specified on the <literal>process-definition</literal>.
    Tasks specified on the process definition can be looked up by name and 
    referenced from within <literal>task-node</literal>s or used from 
    inside actions. In fact, all tasks (also in task-nodes) that are given a 
    name can be looked up by name in the process-definition.
    </para>
    
    <para>Task names must be unique in the whole process definition. Tasks 
    can be given a <literal>priority</literal>.  This priority will be used 
    as the initial priority for each task instance that is created for this task.  
    TaskInstances can change this initial priority afterward.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="taskinstances">
    <title>Task instances</title>
    
    <para>A task instance can be assigned to an actorId (java.lang.String).  All task instances
    are stored in one table of the database (JBPM_TASKINSTANCE).  By querying this table for 
    all task instances for a given actorId, you get the task list for that particular user.
    </para>
    
    <para>The jBPM task list mechanism can combine jBPM tasks with other tasks, even when those
    tasks are unrelated to a process execution.  That way jBPM developers can easily combine 
    jBPM-process-tasks with tasks of other applications in one centralized task-list-repository.
    </para>
    
    <section id="taskinstancelifecycle">
      <title>Task instance life-cycle</title>
      <para>The task instance life-cycle is straightforward: After creation, task instances can optionally 
      be started.  Then, task instances can be ended, which means that the task instance is marked as 
      completed.</para>
      <para>Note that for flexibility, assignment is not part of the life cycle.  So task instances 
      can be assigned or not assigned.  Task instance assignment does not have an influence on the 
      task instance life cycle.</para>
      <para>Task instances are typically created by the process execution entering a 
      <literal>task-node</literal> (with the method <literal>TaskMgmtInstance.createTaskInstance(...)</literal>).
      Then, a user interface component will query the database for the task lists using the 
      <literal>TaskMgmtSession.findTaskInstancesByActorId(...)</literal>. Then, after collecting input 
      from the user, the UI component calls <literal>TaskInstance.assign(String)</literal>, 
      <literal>TaskInstance.start()</literal> or <literal>TaskInstance.end(...)</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>A task instance maintains its state by means of date-properties : <literal>create</literal>, 
      <literal>start</literal> and <literal>end</literal>.  Those properties can be accessed by 
      their respective getters on the <literal>TaskInstance</literal>.</para>
      <para>Currently, completed task instances are marked with an end date so that they are not 
      fetched with subsequent queries for tasks lists.  But they remain in the JBPM_TASKINSTANCE 
      table.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="taskinstancesandgraphexecution">
      <title>Task instances and graph execution</title>
      <para>Task instances are the items in an actor's task list.  Task instances 
      can be signalling.  A signalling task instance is a task instance that, when 
      completed, can send a signal to its token to continue the process execution.  
      Task instances can be blocking, meaning that the related token (=path of 
      execution) is not allowed to leave the task-node before the task instance is 
      completed.  By default task instances are signalling and non-blocking.
      </para>
    
      <para>In case more than one task instance are associated with a task-node,
      the process developer can specify how completion of the task instances affects
      continuation of the process.  Following is the list of values that can be 
      given to the signal-property of a task-node.</para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">last</emphasis>: This is the default.  Proceeds execution when the last task instance is completed. When no tasks are created on entrance of this node, execution is continued.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">last-wait</emphasis>:                  Proceeds execution when the last task instance is completed. When no tasks are created on entrance of this node, execution waits in the task node until tasks are created.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">first</emphasis>:                      Proceeds execution when the first task instance is completed. When no tasks are created on entrance of this node, execution is continued.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">first-wait</emphasis>:                 Proceeds execution when the first task instance is completed. When no tasks are created on entrance of this node, execution waits in the task node until tasks are created.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">unsynchronized</emphasis>: Execution always continues, regardless whether tasks are created or still unfinished.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">never</emphasis>: Execution never continues, regardless whether tasks are created or still unfinished.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    
      <para>Task instance creation might be based upon a runtime calculation.  In that case, add an 
      <literal>ActionHandler</literal> on the <literal>node-enter</literal> event of the <literal>task-node</literal> and 
      set the attribute <literal>create-tasks="false"</literal>.  Here is an example of such an action handler implementation:
      </para>
    
      <programlisting language="java">public class CreateTasks implements ActionHandler {
  public void execute(ExecutionContext executionContext) throws Exception {
    Token token = executionContext.getToken();
    TaskMgmtInstance tmi = executionContext.getTaskMgmtInstance();
      
    TaskNode taskNode = (TaskNode) executionContext.getNode();
    Task changeNappy = taskNode.getTask("change nappy");

    // now, 2 task instances are created for the same task.
    tmi.createTaskInstance(changeNappy, token);
    tmi.createTaskInstance(changeNappy, token);
  }
}</programlisting>

      <para>As shown in the example the tasks to be created can be specified 
      in the task-node.  They could also be specified in the 
      <literal>process-definition</literal> and fetched from the 
      <literal>TaskMgmtDefinition</literal>.  <literal>TaskMgmtDefinition</literal> extends 
      the ProcessDefinition with task management information.</para>
    
      <para>The API method for marking task instances as completed is 
      <literal>TaskInstance.end()</literal>.  Optionally, you can specify a transition 
      in the end method.   In case the completion of this task instance triggers 
      continuation of the execution, the task-node is left over the specified 
      transition.</para>
    
    </section>
    
  </section>

  <section id="assignment">
    <title>Assignment</title>

    <para>A process definition contains task nodes.  A <literal>task-node</literal> 
    contains zero or more tasks.  Tasks are a static description as part of the process 
    definition.  At runtime, tasks result in the creation of task instances.  A task 
    instance corresponds to one entry in a person's task list.</para>
    
    <para>With jBPM, push (personal task list)<footnote><para><xref linkend="thepersonaltasklist"/>.</para></footnote> and 
    pull (group task list)<footnote><para><xref linkend="thegrouptasklist"/>.</para></footnote> model (see below) of 
    task assignment can be applied in combination.  
    The process can calculate the responsible for a task and push it in his/her task list.
    Or alternatively, a task can be assigned to a pool of actors, in which case 
    each of the actors in the pool can pull the task and put it in the actor's 
    personal task list.
    </para>
    
    <section id="assignmentinterfaces">
      <title>Assignment interfaces</title>
      <para>Assigning task instances is done via the interface 
      <literal>AssignmentHandler</literal>:</para>
    
      <programlisting language="java">public interface AssignmentHandler extends Serializable {
  void assign( Assignable assignable, ExecutionContext executionContext );
}</programlisting>

      <para>An assignment handler implementation is called when a task instance is 
      created.  At that time, the task instance can be assigned to one or more actors.  
      The <literal>AssignmentHandler</literal> implementation should 
      call the <literal>Assignable</literal> methods (<literal>setActorId</literal> or 
      <literal>setPooledActors</literal>) to assign a task.  The <literal>Assignable</literal> is either 
      a <literal>TaskInstance</literal> or a <literal>SwimlaneInstance</literal> (=process role).
      </para>
    
      <programlisting language="java">public interface Assignable {
  public void setActorId(String actorId);
  public void setPooledActors(String[] pooledActors);
}</programlisting>

      <para>Both <literal>TaskInstance</literal>s
      and <literal>SwimlaneInstance</literal>s can be assigned to a specific user or to a pool 
      of actors.  To assign a TaskInstance to a user, call 
      <literal>Assignable.setActorId(String actorId)</literal>. To assign a TaskInstance to a pool
      of candidate actors, call <literal>Assignable.setPooledActors(String[] actorIds)</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>Each task in the process definition can be associated with an assignment
      handler implementation to perform the assignment at runtime.</para>
      <para>When more than one task in a process should be assigned to the same person 
      or group of actors, consider the usage of a swimlane<footnote><para><xref linkend="swimlanes"/>.</para></footnote></para>
      <para>To allow for the creation of reusable <literal>AssignmentHandler</literal>s,
      each usage of an <literal>AssignmentHandler</literal> can be configured in 
      the <literal>processdefinition.xml</literal>.  See <xref linkend="delegation" /> 
      for more information on how to add configuration to assignment handlers.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="theassignmentdatamodel">
      <title>The assignment data model</title>
      <para>The data model for managing assignments of task instances and swimlane instances to 
      actors is the following.  Each <literal>TaskInstance</literal> has an actorId
      and a set of pooled actors.</para>
      
      <figure id="assignment.model.image">
        <title>The assignment model class diagram</title>
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/assignment.model.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The actorId is the responsible for the task, while the 
      set of pooled actors represents a collection of candidates that can become responsible 
      if they would take the task.  Both actorId and pooledActors are optional and can 
      also be combined.</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="thepersonaltasklist">
      <title>The personal task list</title>
      <para>The personal task list denotes all the task instances that are assigned to a specific individual.
      This is indicated with the property <literal>actorId</literal> on a <literal>TaskInstance</literal>.  So 
      to put a TaskInstance in someone's personal task list, you just use one of the following ways:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Specify an expression in the attribute <literal>actor-id</literal> of the task element in the process</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Use TaskInstance.setActorId(String) from anywhere in your code</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Use assignable.setActorId(String) in an AssignmentHandler</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>To fetch the personal task list for a given user, use <literal>TaskMgmtSession.findTaskInstances(String actorId)</literal>.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="thegrouptasklist">
      <title>The group task list</title>
      <para>The pooled actors denote the candidates for the task instance. This means that the task is offered to many users 
      and one candidate has to step up and take the task.  Users can not start working on tasks in their group task list 
      immediately.  That would result in a potential conflict that many people start working on the same task.  To prevent this,
      users can only take task instances of their group task list and move them into their personal task list.  Users are only 
      allowed to start working on tasks that are in their personal task list.
      </para>
      <para>To put a taskInstance in someone's group task list, you must put the user's actorId or one of the user's 
      groupIds in the pooledActorIds.  To specify the pooled actors, use one of the following:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Specify an expression in the attribute <literal>pooled-actor-ids</literal> of the task element in the process</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Use TaskInstance.setPooledActorIds(String[]) from anywhere in your code</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Use assignable.setPooledActorIds(String[]) in an AssignmentHandler</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>To fetch the group task list for a given user, proceed as follows: Make a collection that includes the user's actorId 
      and all the ids of groups that the user belongs to. With <literal>TaskMgmtSession.findPooledTaskInstances(String actorId)</literal> or
      <literal>TaskMgmtSession.findPooledTaskInstances(List actorIds)</literal> you can search for task instances that are not in a personal 
      task list (actorId==null) and for which there is a match in the pooled actorIds.  
      </para>
      <para>The motivation behind this is that we want to separate the identity component from jBPM task assignment. jBPM only stores 
      Strings as actorIds and doesn't know the relation between the users, groups and other identity information.
      </para>
      
      <para>The actorId will always override the pooled actors.  So a taskInstance that has an actorId and a list of pooledActorIds,
      will only show up in the actor's personal task list.  Keeping the pooledActorIds around allows a user to put a task instance
      back into the group by just setting the actorId property of the taskInstance to <literal>null</literal>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="taskinstancevariables">
    <title>Task instance variables</title>
    <para>A task instance can have its own set of variables and a task instance can 
      also 'see' the process variables.  Task instances are usually created in an execution 
      path (=token).  This creates a parent-child relation between the token and the task 
      instance similar to the parent-child relation between the tokens themselves.  
      The normal scoping rules apply between the variables of a task instance and the 
      process variables of the related token.  More info about scoping can be found 
      in <xref linkend="variablescopes" />.
    </para>
    <para>This means that a task instance can 'see' its own variables plus all the variables 
      of its related token.
    </para>
    <para>The controller can be used to create, populate and submit variables between 
      the task instance scope and the process scoped variables.
    </para>
  </section>
    
  <section id="taskcontrollers">
    <title>Task controllers</title>
    <para>At creation of a task instance, the task controllers can populate the task instance variables 
      and when the task instance is finished, the task controller can submit the data of the 
      task instance into the process variables.
    </para>
    <para>Note that you are not forced to use task controllers.  Task instances also are able 
      to 'see' the process variables related to its token.  Use task controllers when you want 
      to:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>a) create copies of variables in the task instances so that intermediate updates 
        to the task instance variables don't affect the process variables until the process 
        is finished and the copies are submitted back into the process variables.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>b) the task instance variables do not relate one-on-one with the process variables.
        E.g. suppose the process has variables 'sales in January' 'sales in February' and 'sales in march'.
        Then the form for the task instance might need to show the average sales in the 3 months.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Tasks are intended to collect input from users.  But there are many user interfaces
      which could be used to present the tasks to the users. E.g. a web application, a swing application,
      an instant messenger, an email form,...  So the task controllers make the bridge between the 
      process variables (=process context) and the user interface application.  The task controllers 
      provide a view of process variables to the user interface application.
    </para>
    <para>The task controller makes the translation (if any) from the process variables to the 
      task variables.  When a task instance is created, the task controller is responsible for extracting 
      information from the process variables and creating the task variables.  The task variables serve 
      as the input for the user interface form.  And the user input can be stored in the task variables.
      When the user ends the task, the task controller is responsible for updating the process 
      variables based on the task instance data.
    </para>
    <figure id="task.controllers.image">
      <title>The task controllers</title>
      <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/task.controllers.jpg"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>In a simple scenario, there is a one-on-one mapping between process variables and the 
      form parameters.  Task controllers are specified in a task element.  
      In this case, the default jBPM task controller can be used and it takes a list of 
      <literal>variable</literal> elements inside.  The variable elements express 
      how the process variables are copied in the task variables.
    </para>
    
    <para>The next example shows how you can create separate task instance variable copies
      based on the process variables:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;task name=&quot;clean ceiling&quot;&gt;
  &lt;controller&gt;
    &lt;variable name=&quot;a&quot; access=&quot;read&quot; mapped-name=&quot;x&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;variable name=&quot;b&quot; access=&quot;read,write,required&quot; mapped-name=&quot;y&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;variable name=&quot;c&quot; access=&quot;read,write&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/controller&gt;
&lt;/task&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The <literal>name</literal> attribute refers to the name of the process variable.  
      The <literal>mapped-name</literal> is optional and refers to the name of the task instance 
      variable.  If the mapped-name attribute is omitted, mapped-name defaults to the name.
      Note that the mapped-name also is used as the label for the fields in the task instance 
      form of the web application.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <literal>access</literal> attribute specifies if the variable is copied at task instance
      creation, will be written back to the process variables at task end and whether it is 
      required. This information can be used by the user interface to generate the proper
      form controls.  The access attribute is optional and the default 
      access is 'read,write'. 
    </para>
    
    <para>A <literal>task-node</literal> can have many tasks and a <literal>start-state</literal> can have 
      1 task.
    </para>
    
    <para>If the simple one-to-one mapping between process variables and form parameters is too limiting, you 
      can also write your own TaskControllerHandler implementation.  Here's the TaskControllerHandler interface:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting language="java">public interface TaskControllerHandler extends Serializable {
  void initializeTaskVariables(TaskInstance taskInstance, ContextInstance contextInstance, Token token);
  void submitTaskVariables(TaskInstance taskInstance, ContextInstance contextInstance, Token token);
}</programlisting>
    
    <para>And here's how to configure your custom task controller implementation in a task:</para>
    
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;task name=&quot;clean ceiling&quot;&gt;
  &lt;controller class=&quot;com.yourcom.CleanCeilingTaskControllerHandler&quot;&gt;
    -- here goes your task controller handler configuration --
  &lt;/controller&gt;
&lt;/task&gt;</programlisting>
  </section>

  <section id="swimlanes">
    <title>Swimlanes</title>
    <para>A swimlane is a process role.  It is a mechanism to specify that 
    multiple tasks in the process should be done by the same actor.  So 
    after the first task instance is created for a given swimlane, the actor 
    should be remembered in the process for all subsequent tasks that are in 
    the same swimlane.  A swimlane therefore has one 
    <literal>assignment</literal><footnote><para><xref linkend="assignment"/>.</para></footnote>
    and all tasks that reference a swimlane should not specify an 
    <literal>assignment</literal><footnote><para><xref linkend="assignment"/>.</para></footnote>. 
    </para>
    
    <para>When the first task in a given swimlane is created, the 
    <literal>AssignmentHandler</literal> of the swimlane is called.
    The <literal>Assignable</literal> that is passed to the <literal>AssignmentHandler</literal>
    will be the <literal>SwimlaneInstance</literal>.  Important to know is that 
    all assignments that are done on the task instances in a given swimlane will 
    propagate to the swimlane instance.  This behavior is implemented as the default 
    because the person that takes a task to fulfilling a certain process role will
    have the knowledge of that particular process.  So all subsequent assignments 
    of task instances to that swimlane are done automatically to that user.
    </para>
    
    <para>Swimlane is a terminology borrowed from UML activity diagrams.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="swimlaneinstarttask">
    <title>Swimlane in start task</title>
    <para>A swimlane can be associated with the start task to capture the process 
    initiator.</para>
    <para>A task can be specified in a start-state.  That task be associated with a 
    swimlane.  When a new task instance is created for such a task, the current 
    authenticated actor will be captured with 
    Authentication.getAuthenticatedActorId()<footnote><para><xref linkend="authentication"/>.</para></footnote>
    and that actor will be stored in the swimlane of the start task.
    </para>
    <para>For example:</para>
    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition&gt;
  &lt;swimlane name='initiator' /&gt;
  &lt;start-state&gt;
    &lt;task swimlane='initiator' /&gt;
    &lt;transition to='...' /&gt;
  &lt;/start-state&gt;
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>Also variables can be added to the start task as with any other task to 
    define the form associated with the task.  See <xref linkend="taskcontrollers"/></para>
  </section>

  <section id="taskevents">
    <title>Task events</title>
    <para>Tasks can have actions associated with them.  There are 4 standard event types defined 
    for tasks: <literal>task-create</literal>, 
    <literal>task-assign</literal>, <literal>task-start</literal> and <literal>task-end</literal>.</para>
    <para><literal>task-create</literal> is fired when a task instance is created.</para>
    <para><literal>task-assign</literal> is fired when a task instance is being assigned.  
    Note that in actions that are executed on this event, you can access the previous 
    actor with <literal>executionContext.getTaskInstance().getPreviousActorId();</literal>
    </para>
    <para><literal>task-start</literal> is fired when <literal>TaskInstance.start()</literal>
    is called.  This can be used to indicate that the user is actually starting to work on this 
    task instance.  Starting a task is optional.</para>
    <para><literal>task-end</literal> is fired when <literal>TaskInstance.end(...)</literal>
    is called.  This marks the completion of the task.  If the task is related to a process 
    execution, this call might trigger the resuming of the process execution.
    </para>
    <para>Since tasks can have events and actions associated with them, also 
    exception handlers can be specified on a task.  For more information about exception 
    handling, see <xref linkend="exceptionhandling" />.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tasktimers">
    <title>Task timers</title>
    <para>As on nodes, timers can be specified on tasks.  See <xref linkend="timers" />.</para>
    <para>The special thing about timers for tasks is that the <literal>cancel-event</literal>
    for task timers can be customized.  By default, a timer on a task will be canceled when 
    the task is ended (=completed).  But with the <literal>cancel-event</literal> attribute
    on the timer, process developers can customize that to e.g. <literal>task-assign</literal>
    or <literal>task-start</literal>.  The <literal>cancel-event</literal> supports multiple
    events.  The <literal>cancel-event</literal> types can be combined by specifying them in a 
    comma separated list in the attribute.</para>
  </section>


  <section id="customizingtaskinstances">
    <title>Customizing task instances</title>
    <para>Task instances can be customized.  The easiest way to do this is
    to create a subclass of <literal>TaskInstance</literal>.  Then create a 
    <literal>org.jbpm.taskmgmt.TaskInstanceFactory</literal> implementation and 
    configure it by setting the configuration property <literal>jbpm.task.instance.factory</literal> 
    to the fully qualified class name in the jbpm.cfg.xml.  If you use a subclass of 
    TaskInstance, also create a hibernate 
    mapping file for the subclass (using the hibernate 
    <literal>extends="org.jbpm.taskmgmt.exe.TaskInstance"</literal>).  Then 
    add that mapping file to the list of mapping files in the 
    <literal>hibernate.cfg.xml</literal></para>
  </section>

  <section id="theidentitycomponent">
    <title>The identity component</title>
    <para>Management of users, groups and permissions is commonly known 
    as identity management. jBPM includes an optional identity component 
    that can be easily replaced by a company's own identity data store.
    </para>

    <para>The jBPM identity management component 
    includes knowledge of the organizational model.
    Task assignment is typically done with organizational knowledge. 
    So this implies knowledge of an organizational model, describing the 
    users, groups, systems and the relations between them.  Optionally, 
    permissions and roles can be included too in an organizational model.
    Various academic research attempts failed, proving that no generic 
    organizational model can be created that fits every organization.
    </para>
    
    <para>The way jBPM handles this is by defining an actor as an actual 
    participant in a process.  An actor is identified by its ID called an 
    actorId.  jBPM has only knowledge about actorIds and they are represented 
    as <literal>java.lang.String</literal>s for maximum flexibility. So any 
    knowledge about the organizational model and the structure of that data 
    is outside the scope of the jBPM core engine.</para>
    <para>As an extension to jBPM we will provide (in the future) a component 
    to manage that simple user-roles model.   This many to many relation between 
    users and roles is the same model as is defined in the J2EE and the servlet 
    specs and it could serve as a starting point in new developments.  People 
    interested in contributing should check the jboss jbpm jira issue tracker
    for more details.</para>

    <para>Note that the user-roles model as it is used in the servlet, ejb and 
    portlet specifications, is not sufficiently powerful for handling 
    task assignments.  That model is a many-to-many relation between
    users and roles.  This doesn't include information about the teams and 
    the organizational structure of users involved in a process.</para>
    
    <section id="theidentitymodel">
      <title>The identity model</title>

      <figure id="identity.model.image">
        <title>The identity model class diagram</title>
        <mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="images/identity.model.gif"/></imageobject></mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The classes in yellow are the relevant classes for the expression 
      assignment handler that is discussed next.</para>

      <para>A <literal>User</literal> represents a user or a service. A 
      <literal>Group</literal> is any kind of group of users.  
      Groups can be nested to model the relation 
      between a team, a business unit and the whole company.  Groups have 
      a type to differentiate between the hierarchical groups and e.g. 
      hair color groups. <literal>Membership</literal>s represent the 
      many-to-many relation between users and groups.  A membership can be 
      used to represent a position in a company.  The name of the membership 
      can be used to indicate the role that the user fulfills in the 
      group.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="assignmentexpressions">
      <title>Assignment expressions</title>
      <para>The identity component comes with one implementation that evaluates an
      expression for the calculation of actors during assignment of tasks. Here's
      an example of using the assignment expression in a process definition:</para>
      
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;process-definition&gt;
  &lt;task-node name='a'&gt;
    &lt;task name='laundry'&gt;
      &lt;assignment expression='previous --> group(hierarchy) --> member(boss)' /&gt;
    &lt;/task&gt;
    &lt;transition to='b' /&gt;
  &lt;/task-node&gt;</programlisting>
      
      <para>Syntax of the assignment expression is like this:</para>
      <programlisting>first-term --> next-term --> next-term --> ... --> next-term

where

first-term ::= previous |
               swimlane(swimlane-name) |
               variable(variable-name) |
               user(user-name) |
               group(group-name)

and 

next-term ::= group(group-type) |
              member(role-name)
</programlisting>
      
      <section id="firstterms">
        <title>First terms</title>
        
        <para>An expression is resolved from left to right.  The first-term specifies 
        a <literal>User</literal> or <literal>Group</literal> in the identity model.  
        Subsequent terms calculate the next term from the intermediate user or 
        group.</para>

        <para><literal>previous</literal> means the task is assigned to the current 
        authenticated actor.  This means the actor that performed the previous step in 
        the process.</para>

        <para><literal>swimlane(swimlane-name)</literal> means the user or group is taken 
        from the specified swimlane instance.</para>
      
        <para><literal>variable(variable-name)</literal> means the user or group is taken 
        from the specified variable instance.  The variable instance can contain a 
        <literal>java.lang.String</literal>, in which case that user or group is fetched from 
        the identity component.  Or the variable instance contains a <literal>User</literal> 
        or <literal>Group</literal> object. </para>
      
        <para><literal>user(user-name)</literal> means the given user is taken from the 
        identity component.</para>
      
        <para><literal>group(group-name)</literal> means the given group is taken from the 
        identity component.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="nextterms">
        <title>Next terms</title>
        
        <para><literal>group(group-type)</literal> gets the group for a user.  Meaning that 
        previous terms must have resulted in a <literal>User</literal>.  It searches for the 
        the group with the given group-type in all the memberships for the user.</para>
        
        <para><literal>member(role-name)</literal> gets the user that performs a given role 
        for a group.  The previous terms must have resulted in a <literal>Group</literal>.  
        This term searches for the user with a membership to the group for which the name 
        of the membership matches the given role-name.</para>
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section id="removingtheidentitycomponent">
      <title>Removing the identity component</title>
      <para>When you want to use your own datasource for organizational 
      information such as your company's user database or LDAP system, 
      you can just rip out the jBPM identity component.  The only thing 
      you need to do is make sure that you delete the line ...</para>
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;mapping resource="org/jbpm/identity/User.hbm.xml"/&gt;
&lt;mapping resource="org/jbpm/identity/Group.hbm.xml"/&gt;
&lt;mapping resource="org/jbpm/identity/Membership.hbm.xml"/&gt;</programlisting>
      
      <para>from the <literal>hibernate.cfg.xml</literal> </para>
      <para>The <literal>ExpressionAssignmentHandler</literal> is dependent on the identity 
      component so you will not be able to use it as is.  In case you want 
      to reuse the <literal>ExpressionAssignmentHandler</literal> and bind it to your user data 
      store, you can extend from the <literal>ExpressionAssignmentHandler</literal> and override
      the method <literal>getExpressionSession</literal>.
      </para>
      <programlisting language="java">protected ExpressionSession getExpressionSession(AssignmentContext assignmentContext);</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>
